こんにちは、クリスと申します。今日はDrupalDEN岩国でスペシャルトークをすることになり、光栄です。 今日は沖縄科学技術大学院大学の
こんにちは、クリスと申します。今日はDrupalDEN岩国でスペシャルトークをすることになり、光栄です。 今日は沖縄科学技術大学院大学の
リニューアルされたウェブサイトを発表します。 英語で技術的な内容を発表した方がやりやすいのですが、
リニューアルされたウェブサイトを発表します。 英語で技術的な内容を発表した方がやりやすいのですが、
それでも後で日本語でお話しして、ご意見をいただくのが楽しみです。
それでも後で日本語でお話しして、ご意見をいただくのが楽しみです。
Good afternoon. My name is Chris
こんにちは、クリスと申します
and my honor to be here to give a special talk today at the DrupalCamp Iwakuni.
本日、DrupalDEN岩国で特別講演をさせていただくことを光栄に思います。
Our University, OIST
本学OISTでは
build the Drupal 7 site in 2011,
Drupal 7のリリース初年度の2011年にサイトを構築しました。
which was the first year of its release.
サイトを構築しました。
Drupal 7 had the longest lifespan among all the versions,
Drupal 7はすべてのDrupalのバージョンの中で最も長い寿命を持ち、
and brought significant changes to this platform.
プラットフォームに大きな変化をもたらしました。
One of these change was the integration of CCK as the content type entity field.
これらの変更の1つは、Content TypeのエンティティフィールドとしてCCKが統合され、
It brought test-driven development to the core.
Viewsがコアにもたらされたことです。
Additionally, ImageCache was transformed into that ImageStyle.
さらに、ImageCacheはImage Styleに生まれ変わりました。
Last year,
昨年、
we underwent a two-year journey to rebuild and modernize the website using Drupal 9.
私たちはDrupal 9を使用してウェブサイトを再構築するための2年間の旅を経験しました。
In the first part of the talk I will discuss the development and the project management process went through during the website rebuild.
講演の前半では、Webサイトの再構築の際に行った開発とプロジェクト管理のプロセスについて説明します。
In the second part of my talk,
第二部では
will delve deeper into the challenges we faced when localizing the website
英語と日本語のバイリンガルに向けたウェブサイトのローカライズで
for our bilingual English and Japanese audiences.
直面した課題について、より深く掘り下げます。
I will share the issue we encountered beyond just translation, and how we address them to provide the best experience to our users.
また、単なる翻訳にとどまらず、どのような問題に直面したのか。 どのように対処し、ユーザーに最高のユーザーエクスペリエンスを提供したかをお話しします。
First.
まず、
a little bit about myself.
僕のことを少しご紹介します。
I'm a Drupal developer with 14 years of experience in Drupal development.
私はDrupalの開発者で、14年の経験があります。
I have extensive experience in web design and development in traditional Chinese, Japanese, and English.
繁体字中国語、日本語、英語でのウェブデザインと開発の経験が豊富です。
I'm also a member of the Drupal community, and a former group leader in Taiwan
Drupalコミュニティのメンバーでもあり、台湾の元グループリーダーでもあります。
Outside of Drupal, I'm also interested in coffee, Germany, and cats, and welcome any conversation about those topics as well.
Drupal以外では、コーヒー、ドイツ、猫に興味があり、これらのトピックについての会話も歓迎します。
Before jumping to the topic.
本題に入る前に
Please note that any mention of the vendor or products in this talk are not endorsement
この講演でベンダーやサービスについての言及があっても、それを推奨するものではないことにご了承ください。
Our old Drupal 7 side served us well. Bringing in over 30 million visits,
Drupal 7の旧サイトは、私たちによく貢献してくれました。3,000万人以上の訪問者と
and deliver 37,000 pieces of mountain.
37,000のコンテンツを提供しました。
In the last 3 years we doubled our monthly visit.
この3年間で月間の訪問者数が2倍になりました。
The website shares our accomplishment with the world, such as when we have a new lab building were completed
このサイトでは、私たちの成果を世界に発信しています。 例えば、新しい研究棟が完成したとき。
when we received high impact rankings in Nature, and when our faculty member won the Nobel Prize recently.
Nature誌で高い影響力を持つランキングを獲得したとき。ノーベル賞受賞などの成果を世界に発信しました。
The website continuously to celebrate the success.
私たちの成功を継続的に祝うサイトです。
However, we continue to strive for innovation and shape the future of research in Japan.
しかし、私たちはこれからもイノベーションに努め、日本の研究の未来を切り開いていきます。
In order to reach these goals.
これらの目標を達成するために
We have to set the new objectives and needed a new website that could deliver our outcome in a more effective and flexible way.
新しい目標を設定し、その成果をより効果的かつ柔軟に提供できる新しいウェブサイトが必要です。より効果的で柔軟な方法で、私たちの成果をお届けすることができます。
In 2020 OIST set a
2020年、沖縄科学技術大学院大学は戦略計画を定め
emphasize the 3 pillar of activities: Research, Education, and Innovation.
活動の3本柱を重視するようになりました。研究、教育、そしてイノベーション。
It is also our responsibility to raise the awareness of STEM education, contribute to Okinawa and conduct outreach activities in the Japanese society.
また、STEM教育への関心を高め、沖縄に貢献することも私たちの責務です。そして、日本社会へのアウトリーチ活動も私たちの責務です。
Throughout the entire project, we kept these 3 main pillars in mind
プロジェクト全体を通して この3つの柱を常に意識しています。
and made sure that all the website aligned with the organization strategics.
プロジェクト全体を通して、この3つの柱を念頭に置き、Webサイトが組織の戦略に合致するようにしました。
From a technical perspective, our goal was to improve the accountant management experience for editors.
技術的な面では、編集者のコンテンツ管理体験を向上させることが目標でした。
Drupal 9 allows us to use the media library to manage assets
Drupal 9では、メディアライブラリを使ってアセットを管理できるようになりました。
and change the Node translation method to field translation.
また、ノードの翻訳方法をフィールド翻訳に変更しました。
In addition to Drupal, we also implement a design system to maintain the consistency in user experience and enable editors to easily reuse web component when creating content.
また、Drupalだけでなく、デザインシステムも導入し、ユーザーエクスペリエンスの一貫性を保つようにしました。また、Drupalの他にも、ユーザーエクスペリエンスの一貫性を保つためにデザインシステムを導入し、コンテンツ制作時にWebコンポーネントを簡単に再利用できるようにしました。
The website project was divided into 3 main phases.
Webサイトプロジェクトは、大きく3つのフェーズに分かれていました。
We conducted a comprehensive user research with a vendor in December, 2020 to gain better understanding of the stakeholders, both internal and external users.
2020年12月にベンダーと共同で包括的なユーザー調査を実施し を実施し、社内外のユーザーであるステークホルダーへの理解を深めました。
The study helped us identify how users perceive us.
この調査により、ユーザーが私たちをどのように認識しているのかが明らかになりました。
and how we can improve the website information architecture
と、ウェブサイトの情報アーキテクチャをどのように改善すればよいかを明らかにしました。
In the second phase we hire another vendor to migrate the content and build a new website using Drupal 9.
第2フェーズでは Drupal 9を使用した新しいWebサイトの構築とコンテンツの移行を別のベンダーに依頼しました。
After the vendor completed the development.
ベンダーが開発を完了した後、
our web team took over the content.
当社のウェブチームがコンテンツを引き継ぎました。
We convert it and recreate the content and train the content owner on how to use the new website.
私たちはそれを変換してコンテンツを作り直し、コンテンツ所有者に新しいウェブサイトの使い方をトレーニングしています。
Our developer and I also work on updating and resolving any additional issues.
また、開発者と私は、更新作業と追加問題の解決に取り組みます。
Last December, 2 years after we began the project, we successfully relaunch the website.
プロジェクト開始から2年後の昨年12月、無事リニューアルを果たしました。
It has been well received by the OIST community.
OISTのコミュニティからも好評をいただいています。
Let's take a quick tour of the site now
それでは、早速サイトを覗いてみましょう。
We redefine the color scheme and use the new web component throughout the site.
カラースキームを再定義し、サイト全体に新しいウェブコンポーネントを使用しました。
The Mega menu provide the user with a better navigation map.
メガメニューは、ユーザーにより良いナビゲーションマップを提供します。
Our media editor can mainly select the related content, or let the system choose a related content for them.
メディア・エディターは、関連コンテンツを手動で選択することも、システムに関連コンテンツを選択させることも可能です。
We integrate the flickr into the site
フリッカーをサイトに統合し
to allow us to preview our photo albums
ユーザーが写真集をプレビューできるようにしました。
for different campaign or special committees.
さまざまなキャンペーンや特別委員会のために、
We have a microsite feature
マイクロサイト機能を設け、
which allows them to manage their own content and display their own logo.
独自のコンテンツを管理し、独自のロゴを表示できるようにしました。
Finally, we have also created a style guide to showcase the components
最後に、私たちがウェブサイトのためにデザインしたコンポーネントを紹介するスタイルガイドも
we design for the website.
作成しました。
Now let's moved on to the technical aspect of our project.
さて、次は技術的な面です。
I would like to provide a high-level overview of the migration process, and how we manage the Development project.
ここでは、マイグレーションプロセスの概要と、開発プロジェクトの管理方法について説明したいと思います。
Migration was the first and the most important factor in our project.
マイグレーションは、私たちのプロジェクトにおいて最初にして最も重要な要素でした。
All important content and assets need to be migrated.
重要なコンテンツや資産はすべて移行する必要があります。
It wasn't just about migrating the content node. We also had to migrate files and image that were not managing in the CMS.
コンテンツノードの移行だけでなく、CMSで管理されていないファイルや画像も移行する必要がありました。
In Drupal 7,
Drupal 7 では。Media Libraryがありませんでした。
there was no Media Library, so we used the "Video" and "Photo" content type to contain assets, and later use the short code to reference them in the content body.
そのため、アセットを格納するために「video」と「photo」コンテンツタイプを使用しました。そして、コンテンツ本文の中でショートコードを使ってそれらを参照していました。
This means we had to migrate all 3,000 content nodes and over 6,000 media assets first.
つまり、まず3,000のコンテンツノードと6,000以上のメディアアセットをすべて移行する必要がありました。
and then convert all the inline circle into the new media embed format.
そして、インラインのショートコードをすべて新しいメディア埋め込み形式に変換する必要がありました。
In the past,
これまでコンテンツエディターは、
content editors were able to use the IMCE to upload the files and image to the server directly.
IMCEを利用してファイルや画像を直接サーバーにアップロードすることができました。
During the migration we converted over 1,500 inline file sources into media types,
今回の移行では、1,500以上のインラインファイルソースをメディアタイプに変換しました。
including images, documents, and embedded videos. This not only ensure that all the files in the managed system, but also
これには画像、ドキュメント、埋め込み動画が含まれます。これにより、すべてのファイルが管理されたシステム内にあることが保証されるだけでなく、
makes the system more secure.
システムの安全性も向上しました。
In total, we migrate more than 10,000 content and assets via the Drupal Migrate API script.
Drupal Migrate APIスクリプトを利用して、合計で10,000以上のコンテンツやアセットを移行しています。
The migrate profile was kept in use in the project to provide mockup data for testing purpose.
移行プロファイルは、テスト目的のモックアップデータを提供するために、プロジェクトで使い続けました。
During each feature development, our local environment and cloud CI environment builds the site with the mockup data every time.
各新機能の開発中ローカル環境とクラウドCI環境では、毎回モックアップデータを使用してサイトを構築しています。
This allows us to run the unit test repeatedly
これにより、ユニットテストを繰り返し実行し、
and make our deployment more robust and reliable.
より堅牢で信頼性の高いデプロイメントを実現することができました。
Migration was critical to the project.
移行はプロジェクトにとって重要であり、
and require a lot of efforts to review, content, and validate the results but it was worth it.
内容の確認や結果の検証に多くの労力を要しました。しかし、その価値はあり、
and play the crucial role in the project's success.
プロジェクトの成功に重要な役割を果たしました。
Beyond migration,
移行にとどまらず、
There were 3 keys that make the project success.
プロジェクトを成功に導いた3つの鍵があります。
We made sure to keep our team and the Supervisor informed of our progress.
私たちは、チームと上司に進捗状況を常に伝えるようにしました。
OIST is a large organization, with many decision making channel. So when necessary, we met the stakeholder directly, and then find someone who could support and communicate
OISTは大きな組織であり、多くの意思決定ルートがあります。そのため、必要に応じてステークホルダーと直接面談を行いました。
to the right channel.
また、適切なルートでサポートし、コミュニケーションを取れる人を探しました。
We use a tool effectively to manage project tasks and assist with the communication.
プロジェクトのタスクを管理し、コミュニケーションを支援するツールを効果的に使っています。
There is no best tool but we find the right tool that all team members were willing to use.
ベストなツールはありませんが、チームメンバー全員が喜んで使える適切なツールを探しました。
To reduce repetitive tasks and risks,
繰り返しの作業とリスクを減らすために、
we rely on test and automation process as much as possible.
私たちはテストとプロセスの自動化に可能な限り頼っています。
All these factors work together to make the project a success.
これら全ての要素が相まって、プロジェクトは成功するのです。
During the first stage of the project, when we work with the vendor
プロジェクトの最初の段階で、
they use the Github and its project tool to manage the tasks.
ベンダーはGitHubとそのProjectツールを使ってタスク管理を行いました。
This allowed their developer and us to communicate freely
これにより、開発者と私たちは、プロジェクトマネージャーを通したコミュニケーションだけでなく、
rather than only through the project manager.
自由にコミュニケーションをとることができるようになりました。
This accelerate development made the work transparent and increase the mutual trust.
これにより、開発のスピードアップ、作業の透明化、相互の信頼関係の向上が図られました。
After the project was delivered, we introduced Shortcut to manage both development and content creation tasks on the same platform
納品後は、Shortcutを導入し、開発とコンテンツ制作の両タスクを同じプラットフォームで管理するようにしました。
With Shortcut, we were able to integrate Github to track the status of the PR and syncing development task status.
Shortcutでは、GitHubを統合してプルリクエストの状況を把握し、開発タスクの状況を同期させることができました。
Many of us already familiar with Github and their project managed tool have been more mature and user-friendly, now.
GitHubはすでに多くの人が知っており、そのプロジェクト管理ツールはより成熟し、使いやすくなっています。
Shortcut is a task management system that can easily manage both development and editing tasks.
Shortcutは開発作業と編集作業の両方を簡単に管理できるタスク管理システムです。
Given that the task of development and editing require different workflow,
開発と編集のタスクはそれぞれ異なるワークフローを必要とすることから、
we can create different workflow in shortcut for them.
Shortcutでそれぞれ異なるワークフローを作成し、
and then bring them into the same epic or iteration easily.
それらを同じEpicやIterationに簡単に取り込むことができます。
This is very helpful for a team with multiple functions.
これは、複数の機能を持つチームにとって非常に便利な機能です。
In shortcut. We can quickly sync the status of dev tasks with Github.
Shortcutで Githubと開発タスクのステータスを素早く同期させることができますね。
even though they are two separate platform, we can work between them seamlessly.
別々のプラットフォームでありながら、両者の間でシームレスに仕事ができるのです。
We are a two-developer development team and need to focus on tasks and resolving issues.
2人の開発者で構成される開発チームであり、開発タスクと問題解決に集中する必要があります。
The CI/CD process act as a third developer.
CI/CDプロセスは第3の開発者の役割を果たし、
checking the code standard and deploying the code for us.
コーディング標準をチェックし、私たちに代わってコードをデプロイしてくれます。
This allow our developer to quickly move on to the next task after committing the code to the online development environment.
これにより、開発者はコードをオンライン開発環境にコミットした後、次のタスクに素早く移ることができます。
Once the commit passed the CI/CD workflow,
コミットがCI/CDワークフローを通過したら、
we can then focus on reviewing the logic of the code in pull request.
あとはプルリクエストでコードのロジックのレビューに専念し、
And then ask the CI/CD to deploy it to the production site.
CI/CDに本番環境へのデプロイを依頼することができるのです。
With all the tools, script, and continuous communication.
ツール、スクリプト、そして継続的なコミュニケーションにより、
we were able to complete the project smoothly.
プロジェクトをスムーズに完了させることができました。
Of course, the diligent team members
もちろん、勤勉なチームメンバーの存在が、
were the core of the project's success.
プロジェクト成功の核となった。
OIST is a unique graduate university in Japan, with over 50% of our
OISTは、職員や学生を含め、メンバーの50％以上が
members being international, including employees and students.
外国人であるという、日本ではユニークな大学院大学です。
Our Cell signal Unit is a diverse example.
私たちの細胞シグナルユニットもその例にもれず、
With the leading faculty. fellow researchers and students from different countries.
第一線の教授陣、研究仲間、そして学生も世界各国から集まっています。
As a result,
そのため、
English and Japanese are equally important at OIST,
OISTでは英語と日本語が同じくらい重要視されており、
and most of the content on our website is translated into both languages
ホームページのコンテンツもほとんどが両言語に翻訳されています。
During the project we dealt with many translations issues, and in the second part of this talk.
プロジェクト期間中、私たちは多くの翻訳問題に取り組みました。
I'd like to focus on a few of them, particularly for our Japanese and APAC region attendees today.
本講演の第二部では、特に日本やAPAC地域の参加者のために、そのうちのいくつかに焦点を当てたいと思います。
Drupal has well-defined translation system in core.
Drupalはコアにしっかりとした翻訳システムを持っています。
Depends on your experience and role.
あなたの経験や役割に応じて、
There are always ways for you to make translations
翻訳を行う方法は常にあります。
As a site builder,
サイト構築者として、
We can translate nodes with the field translation enabled.
フィールド翻訳を有効にしたノードを翻訳することができます。
Also, we can translate many strings that appears in the user interface.
また、ユーザーインターフェースに表示される多くの文字列を翻訳することができます。
As a themer, we use TWIG to mark translatable sentence with a variable in it.
TWIGを使って、変数が入った翻訳可能な文章をマークしています。
As a developer,
デベロッパーとして
we can mark the translatable string with the t() function.
開発者としては、t()関数で翻訳可能な文字列をマークすればいいのです。
It is also capable to use dynamic variable in the sentence.
文中で動的変数を使用することも可能です。
However, there might be a chance that we need a translation context,
しかし、単語が動詞であったり名詞であったり、
because a word could be verb or noun, or has more than one meaning.
複数の意味を持つため、翻訳文脈が必要な場合がある。
For example,
例えば
"Contact"
"コンタクト"
It will be translated into two different words in Japanese
日本語では2種類の言葉に翻訳されます
as the action "コンタクト"
アクションとして、「コンタクト」。
or as a section label in "連絡先".
セクションラベルとしては、"連絡先 "です。
There are more details about localizing user experience in my talk at the latest DrupalCon Prague.
ユーザーエクスペリエンスのローカライズについては、最新のDrupalCon Pragueでの私の講演に詳細があります。
If you're interested and work on bilingual sites often, it would be helpful for you. But today I want to focus on the issues specific to the project and related to the Japanese languages.
もし、あなたが興味を持っていて、バイリンガルサイトによく携わっているのであれば、参考になるかと思います。しかし、今日はプロジェクト特有の、日本語に関連する問題に焦点を当てたいと思います。
One issue to consider is the date format
考慮すべき問題のひとつは、日付の形式です
in Japan
日本や
as well as in Taiwan.
台湾では、
We typically use a format that starts with the year followed by the months and day.
年、月、日の順に記載する形式が一般的です。
In the other country we often see this date format.
海外では、国によって
which can be interpreted
9月12日とも12月9日とも
as either September 12th or December 9th, depending on the country. For example, most European countries read it as December 9th, while the United States.
解釈される日付形式をよく見かけます。例えば、ヨーロッパの多くの国では12月9日と読みますが、
read it as September 12th.
アメリカでは9月12日と読みます。
Given the diversity of our University members.
OISTのメンバーの多様性を考えると、
we have to find a common way to ensure our understanding of information is consistent.
情報の理解を一致させるために共通の方法を見つけなければなりません。
Therefore we use the ISO 8601 format in English UI, as it is the same order
そのため、英語版UIではISO 8601形式を使用します。
of format for the Japanese UI.
というのは、日本語のUIでも同じ順序でフォーマットされているからです。
Another issue to consider is typing in Japanese, Chinese, or Korean, often referred to as CJK languages.
また、日本語、中国語、韓国語（CJK言語と呼ばれることもあります）の入力も重要な課題です。
Typing Roman alphabet on a keyboard is relatively easy. But how are words typed in CJK languages?
キーボードでローマ字を打つのは比較的簡単ですが、CJK言語ではどのように文字を打つのでしょうか。
Here are some paragraph in CJK about "What to do if you receive the positive COVID-19 notification from the Health Center".
ここでは、"保健所からCOVID-19陽性の通知を受けたらどうするか "について、日中韓の言語でいくつかの段落を紹介します。
you can see
CJK言語では、
the sentence rarely have spaces.
文に空白が入ることはほとんどありません。
To index the content to the database and make it easy to search.
内容をインデックス化し、検索しやすくするために、
Sometimes we need extra treatment.
通常は余分な処理が必要である。
So how do we type? What's this CJK keyboard looks like?
では、日中韓のキーボードはどうなっているのだろうか。
From the left to right
左から右へ
we see two traditional Chinese keyboards.
繁体字中国語のキーボードが2つありますね。
and there are two Korean keyboards layouts, and two Japanese layouts, one in mobile, and the other one is a compact keyboard with the 50
そして、携帯電話には韓国語キーボードと日本語キーボードの2つのレイアウト、つまり50音順のコンパクトなキーボードレイアウト
essential sounds characters.
があります。
For those who don't understand the language.
知らない人にとっては、
They may look like a puzzle, right?
パズルのように見えるかもしれませんね。
When typing the words, the keystrokes vary.
単語を入力する際、キーストロークが異なる。
For the word "Computer".
「コンピュータ」という単語も、
we can also tell. It is different in traditional Chinese used in Taiwan or simplified Chinese in China
台湾の繁体字中国語と中国の簡体字中国語では異なることがわかる。
when typing CJK text, a word is completed only when all the segments is typed.
日中韓の言語を入力する場合、すべてのセグメントを入力して初めて1つの単語が完成する。
Unlike typing English.
英語と違って、
there might be possible worry combination before finish the typing.
入力が完了する前に単語の組み合わせがあるかもしれない。
In this clip
動画の中では、
it shows that inputting
日本語の漢字を入力するには
Japanese kanji requires typing one to four or even more the phonetic elements.
、1～4個、あるいはそれ以上の発音要素を入力する必要があることが示されています。
Additionally.
さらに、
there are different words in Kanji, which have the same pronunciation.
漢字には同じ読みを持つ異なる単語が存在します。
This can lead to an issue in the search box,
このため、検索ボックスでは、
where the search is triggered too early before the actual keyword is completed.
実際にキーワードを入力し終わる前に検索が始まってしまい、
which can be annoying for the users.
ユーザーに迷惑をかけるという問題があります。
This issue can be improved by implementing a special JavaScript event method to wait for the completion of the keyword input
この問題は、JavaScriptの特別なイベントメソッドを実装し、
before the people triggering the search.
キーワード入力の完了を待ってから検索をトリガーすることで改善されます。
In this clip
この動画では、
we can see some improvement.
いくつかの改善が見られました。
We can find the English typing words normally, and the Japanese word for Corona only queries the result when the word is completed.
英語の入力は正常に行われ、日本語の「コロナ」は、単語が完成した時点で初めて検索されることがわかります。
In Drupal, there are autocomplete fields for tags or referencing entities.
Drupalでは、タグや参照する実体のオートコンプリート欄があります。
The core had the issue before, but it was fixed in 2016.
コアには以前からこの問題がありましたが、2016年、
Thanks to the Drupal contributors.
Drupalのコントリビューターのおかげで修正されました。
Mainly, it is the CompositionEvent that helps us to identify the special event when the typing is finished.
主に、入力が終わった時の特別なイベントを特定するために、CompositionEventを使用しています。
When we created this custom autocomplete search box, we had to implement the event as well.
このカスタムオートコンプリート検索ボックスを作成したとき、イベントも実装する必要がありました。
First we detect the starting point of the CJK input method.
まず、CJK入力メソッドの開始位置を検出します。
Next, we wait until the word is decided.
次に、compositionEndイベントが起こるので、
as we see the CompositionEnd event happens.
単語が決定するまで待ちます。
Finally, we send this AJAX request
最後に、このAJAXリクエストを送信します。
After the typing issue. Let's see some sorting issue. In English, we even sort with the alphabet of the title of articles.
タイピングの問題に続いて、ソートの問題を見てみましょう。英語では、記事のタイトル、
taxonomy tags or names, for example.
分類タグ、名前など、アルファベットを使ってソートすることが多い。
However, it is entirely different when sorting in Japanese or Chinese.
しかし、日本語や中国語でソートする場合は、まったく違います。
In Japanese language, most of us know it is
日本語では、五十音の順番で並べ替えることは、
usually order with the 五十音
ほとんどの人が知っています。
and also there are Kanji or Chinese characters, too.
そして、漢字もあります。
when we have an array composed
ある配列の中に、
of Latin letters, numbers, Hiragana, Katagana
アルファベット、数字、ひらがな、カタカナ、
and Kanji.
漢字がある場合、
How do we sort them correctly?
どのようにすれば正しく並べられるのでしょうか。
The ideal order in Japanese language should looks like these on the right.
日本語の理想的な順番は、右のようなものです。
Starting with simple number alphabet like in English, and then Hiragana, Katagana, and the last part the Kanji.
英語のように簡単な数字のアルファベットから始まり、ひらがな、カタカナ、そして最後に漢字。
Hiragana and Katagana follows the order of 五十音. But what is the order in Kanji?
ひらがな、カタカナは五十音の順番で並んでいます。しかし、漢字ではどのような順番になるのでしょうか？
If we use the sort() function directly.
sort()関数を直接使うと、
it will usually sort the array based on an indexed number of each characters in the Unicode table.
Unicodeテーブルの各文字のインデックス番号に基づいて配列がソートされます。
However, this doesn't make sense for Japanese speakers, as the order of the characters doesn't reflect the proper way to sort them in the language.
しかし、これは日本語話者にとっては意味がありません。なぜなら、文字の並び順はその言語での適切な並び方を反映していないからです。
One solution is to use the JavaScript function localeCompare(). this function sorts Kanji based on the pronunciation of the first character
JavaScriptの関数localeCompare()を使えば、最初の文字の読み方に基づいて漢字をソートすることができます。
and then the next character if the first characters is the same
最初の文字が同じなら次の文字も同じにする
In PHP, there is also a similar function to do the sorting, but it is recommended to use a database query for better sorting results from the backend.
PHPにも似たような関数がありますが、バックエンドでよりよいソート結果を得るには、データベースクエリを使用することが推奨されます。
However, this is not perfect yet. There is one word misplaced in the middle
しかし、これは完璧ではなく、真ん中の単語が1つだけ間違っています。
岩下
岩下
It is because the Kanji has another pronunciation.
漢字に別の発音があるからです。
The first characters is read in an alternative way "がん"
最初の文字は「いわ」ではなく、
rather than "いわ"
「がん」と読みます。
Another example, there is another last name can be called either かわの or こうの using the same Kanji.
もうひとつ、同じ漢字で「かわの」「こうの」という名字もあります。
So in Japanese or in Mandarin Chinese the character could have more than one pronunciation.
日本語でも中国語でも、この漢字は複数の発音を持つことができるんですね。
How many characters has more than one pronunciation?
複数の発音を持つ文字はいくつあるのでしょうか？
Japanese country has more than 600 out of 2,000 common characters which has more than one pronounciations.
日本には2,000ある文字のうち、600以上の文字が複数の読み方を持っています。
In the official definition from the Ministry of Education of Taiwan,
台湾の教育部による公式定義では
there were 1,200 out of 5,000 commonly used traditional Chinese characters
一般的に使用される繁体字中国語は5,000字中1,263字であった。
around 10 years ago
10年ほど前に、
officials reviewed and merged many of them, reducing the number down to
その多くを見直し、統合して
Let's take the Kanji for example.
漢字を例にしてみましょう。
It has more pronunciation due to different cultural contexts.
文化的背景が異なるため、より多くの発音がある。
Four of them are inherited from the ancient Chinese in various eras.
そのうちの4つは、様々な時代の古代中国から受け継いだ音読であり、
Another four represent the original Japanese language.
もう4つは本来の日本語の訓読を表している。
The original Chinese character looks very similar.
元の中国語漢字はよく似ていて、
and it has three pronunciations.
3つの発音がある。
The character stands for 樂 (yue) for "music" or 樂 (le) for "happy or happiness", or 樂 (yao) for the verb "to appreciate".
この文字は、「音楽」を表す樂（ユエ）、「幸せ・幸福」を表す樂（ル）、「鑑賞する」という動詞を表す樂（ヤオ）の頭文字をとったものである。
So we
これで
now know Japanese sort by pronunciation. How about Madarin Chinese?
日本語の発音順がわかりましたね。繁体字中国語はどうでしょうか。
Let's bring some delicious Taiwanese food here.
それでは、台湾の美味しいものを紹介しましょう。
They are in the order of
私の好きな順に
my preference
並べてみました。
How do we sort their names using their attribute?
では、属性を使って名前を並べ替えるにはどうしたらいいのでしょう？
Let's first see what options do we have.
まず、どのような方法があるか見てみましょう。
This is the first characters of Iwakuni
これは岩国の一文字
"Yán" in Mandarin.
繁体字中国語で "イェン"。
There are at least four different ways to sort it.
少なくとも4種類の並べ方があります。
We can count its radical strokes.
部首の画数を数える方法、
total strokes.
総画数を数える方法、
spell it with phonetical
台湾でのみ使われている
elements 注音
音素注音で表記する方法、
which is only used in Taiwan, or Pinyin with roman characters which is the main input method in China.
または中国での主な入力方法であるローマ字によるピンインで表記する方法である。
Usually we order with one of the attributes.
通常はいずれかの属性で並び替えを行うが、
And sometimes let the user change the sorting method. For instance, the book search system in a library
図書館の蔵書検索システムのように、ユーザーが並び替えの方法を変更できるようにすることもある。
in traditional Chinese localeCompare() function also works with the various attributes that I mentioned before
繁体字中国語では、localeCompare()は先に述べた様々な属性とも連動します。
By strokes
画数で、
or by the phonetic 注音.
または音声注音で。
This is sorting with the phonetic element 注音. Similar way that we saw Japanese 五十音.
これは音韻の要素である注音でソートしています。五十音で日本語をソートするのと同じようなものです。
It would be difficult to understand, if you don't understand 注音.
注音を理解しないと、理解するのは難しいでしょう。
But the other way be easier.
でも、別の方法はもっと簡単です。
This is sorting in the total strokes.
これは総画数でソートしています。
we can see the first characters of each
左から右へ、最初の文字の
has more strokes from left to right.
ストロークが多くなっているのがわかります。
It's amazing that JavaScript supported, right.
JavaScriptがサポートされてるのがすごいよね。
It is all thanks to the open source contributors, especially in the Unihan project.
これはオープンソースの貢献者のおかげです。特にUniHanプロジェクトは、
a sub branch project
ユニコードのオープンソースプロジェクトの一つです。
That makes this available.
そのおかげで、これが使えるようになったんです。
Let's think about the unresolved issue, what to do with the multiple pronunciation in Kanji?
そこで、未解決の問題を考えてみよう。多読漢字をどうするか？
the issue affects Japanese Kanji, or a Chinese characters when sorting with the phonetic elements 注音 or Pinyin.
この問題は、日本語の漢字、あるいは漢字を発音要素の注音やピンインで並べ替えたときに発生する。
Technically, native speakers know the common variations of the pronunciation.
技術的には、ネイティブスピーカーは、一般的な発音のバリエーションを知っており、
When we process in head, it is processed together.
頭の中で処理する際、一緒に処理されるため、
It doesn't really bother the native speakers when the
異なる発音が混在していても、ネイティブスピーカーは
different pronunciation mixed together.
あまり気にならないのである。
However, my understanding could be wrong about Japanese.
ただし、私の認識が間違っている可能性もありますので、
I would be happy to hear from you what is the pratical solution here.
具体的な解決策をお聞かせいただければと思います。
Sometimes, if the clients request to make it in a explicit order.
もし、クライアントが明示的な順序を要求してきた場合は、
the better way is to map the word into a predefined table or array.
あらかじめ定義されたテーブルや配列に単語をマッピングするのが良い方法です。
At the end, I want to share a sentence with you.
最後に、ある一文を紹介したい。
We hear people say
"Devil is in the details"
"Devil is in the details"
という言葉を耳にすることがある。
It means the difficulty or troubles is not revealed until you look close to the details.
この意味は、「細部にまで目を向けないと、困難や問題は見えてこない」というものである。
The origin of the sentence is somehow opposite.
文の成り立ちが何となく逆なんですよね。
"神は細部に宿る"
"神は細部に宿る"
It is from Germany
ドイツの建築家、
architecture, Mies van der Rohe.
ミース・ファン・デル・ローエの言葉です。
"Der liebe Gott steckt im detail"
"Der liebe Gott steckt im detail" である。
No matter it is devil or God.
悪魔でも神でも、
The sentence has one thing in common.
この文に共通することは一つ。
The most important things are in the details.
一番大事なことは、細かいところにある。
When we see a new website is complete people cheering and feel satisfied.
新しいサイトが完成したとき、人々は歓声を上げ、満足感を覚えます。
When the visitor find the good experience using the website in their native tounge intuitively.
そして、そのウェブサイトを訪れた人が、自分の言語で直感的に操作できることに喜びを感じるとき。
It is all because the developer designer work on every detail to bring the best UX
それは、開発者・デザイナーが最高のUXを実現するために、
to our users.
細部にまでこだわっているからです。
Let's look closer and take the challenge,
そして、よく見て、チャレンジして、
deal with the devil.
悪魔と取引して、
We will find a glorious miracle in the end.
最後には輝かしい奇跡を見つけましょう。
Thank you. I'm. Chris. I wish you a good afternoon today in the following sessions.
どうも、クリスです。今日は以下のセッションで良い午後を過ごせますように。
ご清聴ありがとうございました
ご清聴ありがとうございました。